<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>espresso on Crema on Top - Brewing Espresso at Home</title>
    <link>http://cremaontop.com/categories/espresso/</link>
    <description>Recent content in espresso on Crema on Top - Brewing Espresso at Home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 15:44:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://cremaontop.com/categories/espresso/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Make a Delicious Cup of Faux Espresso with a stove-top Moka Pot in Just 5 Minutes</title>
      <link>http://cremaontop.com/how-to-make-a-delicious-cup-of-faux-espresso-with-a-stove-top-moka-pot-in-just-5-minutes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 15:44:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cremaontop.com/how-to-make-a-delicious-cup-of-faux-espresso-with-a-stove-top-moka-pot-in-just-5-minutes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Moka pots, also known as stovetop espresso makers, are stovetop coffee makers that make a cup of near-espresso coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flavor of coffee made with moka pots is intense and most closely resembles coffee made using an espresso machine. You will find moka pots in most Italian households and they are regarded as a standard part of Italian culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moka pots are usually made of aluminum or stainless steel. They have a bottom chamber for water, a mid-chamber for coffee grounds and a top chamber to hold the brewed coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cremaontop.com/images/image.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;A=Bottom Chamber, B=Middle Chamber or Filter Basket and Funnel, C=Top Chamber for brewed coffee&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;A=Bottom Chamber, B=Middle Chamber or Filter Basket and Funnel, C=Top Chamber for brewed coffee&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can make cappuccinos, lattes and all kinds of espresso drinks with moka pots. They are very easy to use. So, without further ado, let&amp;rsquo;s get started!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you will need:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A stove top (gas or electric) that can produce medium to high heat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A moka pot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water (boiling)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coffee beans - your choice of roast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A grinder to grind your coffee. Never use pre-ground coffee, ever.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional: a scale to weigh your beans (recommended)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Making Moka Pot Coffee (or Stovetop Espresso, or Fauxpresso):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boil your water first. While you are waiting for it to boil, grind your coffee beans - about `18 grams for 2 cups - and place them in the filter funnel. The grounds should be fine, but not very fine, slightly coarser than you would grind for espresso; so about the same coarseness as table salt approximately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, the world was first introduced to using boiling or hot water in the moka pot via World Barista champion James Hoffman in a 2015 youtube video on the ChefSteps channel. The traditional method is to use room-temperature water and let it heat in the moka pot. Pre heating water, according to Hoffman, is a great way to avoid bitter tasting coffee by heating or burning your coffee grounds as the water heats up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fill the bottom chamber of the Moka Pot with the now boiling water, about half-way, just below the pressure release valve. Place the filter funnel over it and screw seal with the top chamber (the one with the handle).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Place the moka pot on a medium to high heat and listen closely, after a while you will hear gurgling . The gurgling sound means your water is boiling and the pressure has built up in the system; your coffee has started to brew.Make sure you listen to the pot so you can hear when gurgling stops. This means your coffee is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remove it from the heat, pour into a cup and enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To turn it into a cappuccino or latte or other milk based drink, simply add steamed or frothed milk to the cup after pouring the coffee. Frothing milk at home without a machine is incredibly simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frothing milk with a French Press:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way is to add warm milk to a french press and rapidly raise the filter and then plunge it back into the milk. Do this for 10-15 seconds. Doing so will introduce air into the milk and you will notice similar micro-foam to the steamed milk you get at a cafe, it might take some practice, but the learning curve is much smaller than learning how to steam milk correctly with a machine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iced Espresso: Your new favourite summer beverage.</title>
      <link>http://cremaontop.com/iced-espresso-the-best-drink-you-will-have-this-summer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 15:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cremaontop.com/iced-espresso-the-best-drink-you-will-have-this-summer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Iced espresso is the perfect drink for beating summer&amp;rsquo;s heat. When you&amp;rsquo;re looking for an uplifting drink and a cup of good ole&#39; coffee just feels wrong under the scorching sun, try an iced espresso, or an iced americano, if you are in the mood for a bigger glass of coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Espresso&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Lemon wedge (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tools:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Espresso Machine,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocktail Shaker,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cups,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ice Cubes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recipe:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pull a shot of espresso and pour it into a cocktail shaker with 2 cubes of ice. Mix, shake until the ice melts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pour into a chilled glass and serve with a slice(s) of lemon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make an iced americano. follow the above recipe and add cold water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tips:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use good quality coffee. The better the beans, the better the taste. I prefer lighter roasts and fruity beans, but that is subjective. What isn&amp;rsquo;t subjective is that freshly roasted (and certainly feshly ground) beans have no substitute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re making ice cubes at home, use distilled or filtered water, as this will create cleaner tasting ice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Brew Good Espresso At Home - Part 1, the machine.</title>
      <link>http://cremaontop.com/how-to-brew-good-espresso-at-home-part-1-the-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 18:18:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://cremaontop.com/how-to-brew-good-espresso-at-home-part-1-the-machine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the right espresso machine and grinder, making a cafe-quality espresso at home is easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A good cup of) Espresso is sometimes seen as a glamorous drink only served in specialty coffee shops, but it is actually quite easy to make at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Espresso machines range from simple and cheap to complicated and expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quality espresso machine, with the help of a good grinder will brew espresso with a rich, syrupy texture as well as the perfect balance of flavor and body.  It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be expensive. Although some of the ones on the higher end tend to produce great results, Pairing a great grinder can turn a cheaper, more entry-level machine into something that can consistently produce coffee that is the envy of your neighborhood cafe&amp;rsquo;s baristas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to select what the right pair of espresso machine and grinder is for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a beginner or you are intimidated by experimentation and new technology, select a super automatic espresso machine.Superautomatics usually come with a built in grinder; you just put in fresh beans, press a button or two and voila! a decent shot of espresso is ready for consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most superautomatics will let you tweak grind size and other settings to try and produce better coffee. With superautomatics, there is a very small learning curve and you will be brewing good (but maybe not great) espresso at home in no time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, that&amp;rsquo;s out of the way, now lets say you are a serious coffee drinker who wants to pull shot after shot of the best espresso you have ever had, and you want to do that at home. You will want a manual/automatic espresso machine. We&amp;rsquo;ll split your options among these into two categories, depending on whether you enjoy pure shots of unadulterated espresso, or you enjoy your coffee as lattes, cappuccinos or other milk-based drinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the straight up espresso lover, the choice is easy, get a single boiler espresso machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cremaontop.com/images/IMG_20181017_233647.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Americano? A single boiler is everything you need.&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Americano? A single boiler is everything you need.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you want to look for one that offers the best possible temperature stability -  A stable temperature ensures even extraction and results in a rich, flavorful espresso. When your machine can not maintain temperature stability, it will result in either under-extracted - watery, acidic coffee or over-extracted - bitter, dull and flavourless coffee that sometimes tastes burnt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single boiler machines can usually also steam milk, but you have to switch the boiler to steaming mode after brewing coffee, wait for it to get up to temperature, it is a hassle - so we&amp;rsquo;d recommend a single boiler for those who like their espresso shots and occasional americanos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like lattes or cappuccinos, you may want to consider a dual boiler machine or a heat exchange espresso machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://cremaontop.com/images/pouring-some-latte-art-1.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Love latte, latte art? Dual Boiler or HX machines are the way to go.&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Love latte, latte art? Dual Boiler or HX machines are the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dual boiler machines have two boilers, you get both a boiler for steam and a separate one for espresso brewing. Dual boiler machines are capable of brewing espresso and steaming milk at the same time. Heat exchange (HX) machines can also brew and steam at the same time. While they come with just one boiler, it is calibrated for steaming milk, a tube which passes through this boiler, carries fresh water which gets heated up to brewing temperature as it reaches the brew-group. Heat exchange machines aren&amp;rsquo;t as temperature stable as dual boiler ones, but with practice, you can learn &amp;lsquo;flush&amp;rsquo; the brew group just the right amount before starting to brew your coffee to get the perfect brewing temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there you have it, three types of machines to consider - Single boiler, dual boiler, and heat exchangers for those serious about home espresso brewing and superautomatics for people just wanting a good cup of joe at the press of a button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above is only part of the whole, for part 2 , we will cover the other, and arguably more important half of home espresso - choosing a grinder that matches your espresso machine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description> 
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>